So I absolutely hate primo. I hate
proviron. I hate SHBG. I hate short
esters. And I hate any type of injection
frequency that isn't daily. Daily is the
only way.
So welcome everyone to the TRT hormone
optimization channel. Uh as you probably
noticed, I am not Steven Devos. Uh I'm
here with Dr. Todd Lee. And uh to get it
out of the way, as far as I'm aware, we
are not related. We could be, but as far
as I'm aware. And uh I actually came
across Todd's content about a month ago.
Basically every day I get a message from
someone on Instagram saying, "What is
this guy like? Is this guy bullshit?"
And I saw this really awesome looking
real cover photo. And I'm like, "Okay."
And then I pop it open and I see a
slaughter to prevail mask hanging in the
background, a Punisher tattoo, and I'm
like, "Fuck, I really hope this guy's
not a Boron because I really want to
like him." And I I ended up watching
I reckon a dozen hours of Todd's content
over the last month. And for anyone
who's wanting to learn anything, not
just about anabolic steroids, but
there's some great content on training,
psychology, nutrition, there's a
fantastic video about how much
testosterone you should take, which
echoes a lot of the stuff that we've
been talking about on this channel for a
long time. So, I'm going to let uh Todd
greet the Earthlings and uh tell us a
bit about uh what got him to be here
today.
>> Greeting Earthlings. So, I'm Todd Lee,
medical doctor, IFBB pro, biochemist,
and I talk a lot of mad [__] and put
down dumb asses and try to educate
people on how to use HRT and steroids as
safely as possible, which is actually
pretty safe if you do it the right way.
And um I've been doing this stuff for 15
years, and the this channel hasn't been
banned yet. the previous channel was in
2018. I sat out for like four years.
Then my friend Paul Barnett talked me
into making a new channel and now we're
back bigger and meaner than ever. So
hopefully I won't hurt your feelings too
bad, but you know what? If the truth
hurts, wear it, right?
>> Absolutely. People uh people need to
hear what they need to hear, not what
they want to hear. And uh not that you'd
agree to it anyway, but I definitely uh
don't want you to speak with a filter
today. I think uh people should hear it
raw and true. So, the first topic that I
want to get into today, and one of the
things I love about your content is that
when you're talking about everything
from testosterone replacement to
anabolic steroids, you talk about daily
dosing. You don't talk about weekly
dosing. You talk about this much per
day. And there's only one other person
in the space who's a good friend of
mine, Dr. Keith Nichols, who has a very
firm belief that testosterone
replacement therapy injections need to
be done daily. And when people look at
the half-life of testosterone, they go,
"Oh, that's not needed." But when you
look at the peak pharmacodnamics, it's
very, very clear that it is. So, I'd
like you to firstly talk about why daily
injections are best and also why SHBG
doesn't really have anything to do with
why people should be injecting daily.
>> Yeah. Everyone's working out these
ridiculous beliefs that make no sense at
all. SHPG is not your friend. It's your
enemy. Basically, it's a reservoir that
hangs on to DHT. And so, if you ever add
in something that's a strong SHBG binder
like Master, then the DHT is going to
flood the system and it's going to cause
hair shedding for a couple days. But a
lot of people [__] out and they stop
taking the Master. They tell everyone
Master causes hair loss. That's really
not what's going on. If you were to use
daily injections of cipionate, a long
acting one, then the levels are smooth.
So, you don't have peaks and trrows. you
don't get the mood swings. Every single
person that trusted me and took that
advice and switched from twice a week
injections or three times a week
injections to daily injections said that
all their every aspect of their life got
better. They had less mood swings that
their basically your DHT and estradiol
will go down at the same dose, but your
total testosterone will go up. And it's
always so funny how these TRT clinics,
they don't know [__] They're basically
pushing this free testosterone nonsense.
That's not relevant at all because the
testosterone that's bound to albumin is
just as biologically available as the
testosterone that's free. It's just that
the free testosterone is going to get
chewed up and spit out faster. The al
the uh the albumin is going to protect
the testosterone and chaperone it
through your system. kind of like IGF
binding protein 3 chaperones IGF through
your system. The SHBG is just garbage.
It just basically mops up the
testosterone. It also forms a complex
with estrogen which binds to your
prostate and then facilitates DHT
causing BPH. That there's I have only
found two people that advocate for SHBG
and I'm not going to say their names,
but that's it. And they're basically in
league with each other. Everyone else on
the planet who knows what they're doing
sees SHPG as a bad thing at the very
least a neutral thing. And so by doing
daily injections with test zip you're
going to wipe out the SHBG from your
system. You know a lot of these guys
they use proviron on cycle because all
it does is mop up SHBG. That's all it's
for. It doesn't it's not anabolic. It
doesn't survive inside the cytoplasm of
the cell. As soon as DHT or proviron
enters the cell, it gets chewed up by 3
alpha HSD, which is an enzyme that
protects the
basically it protects you from growing
too much muscle. So the the the anabolic
the androgenic DHT would be extremely
anabolic if it wasn't for three alpha
HSD
but it's your body chews it up so that
it can't actually bind to the androgen
receptor in the cytool and it can't go
to the nucleus and transcribe and
translate the DNA into protein. The
other steroid that gets chewed up like
that is proviron. It's complete garbage.
It has no anabolic effect. The next
worst steroid would be pro um
primobolin. Primabolan is very
vulnerable to three alpha HSD. That's
why primo is so weak. You know, before
this Primo craze of 2021,
everyone used to laugh about Primo
because it was basically you needed to
use 800 900 a week to see any results
and you would it'd be paying an enormous
amount of money and shooting a whole
bottle a week. It's just garbage. But
now it's so popular. It's [__] weird.
It's like how sometimes there's these
rap artists that have like no talent or
ability. They're just really popular
because they were marketed well. Like
there's um who is that one Hernandez who
had like rainbow colored hair and gold
teeth and he was basically a fake blood
and he was all over the place for like a
couple um Teeshi X9 or something like
that. He's like the primo of the rap
world. It's just like it was just all
marketing and hype and has no actual
substance. So I absolutely hate Primo. I
hate proviryin. I hate SHBG. I hate
short esters. And I hate any type of
injection frequency that isn't daily.
Daily is the only way. If I had like a
religion or a cult, one of the core
tenants would be not skipping leg day.
And the other would be all injections
must be daily.
>> It It's interesting. Back when I was at
university, I used to sell mobile phones
back when you could actually remove the
battery from the phone. And when people
came in with a problem, the first thing
we would ask them is, "Have you tried
taking the battery out and putting the
battery back in?" Because most of the
time that would fix the issue. And I
liken that to increasing injection
frequency. Fixing injection frequency
won't solve, you know, poor eating
habits and alcoholism and morbid
obesity. But when it comes to correcting
the side effects that's caused from the
hormone replacement therapy protocol,
men do not do well with these exertions
of hormone levels. They they they simply
don't it doesn't match our biology. And
when we're looking at the idea that
twice a week injection should be done,
it's basically saying, well, yeah,
that's not going to prevent you from
falling through the therapeutic floor,
sure. Okay. But if you're going up here
and down here every few days, the male
biology is not catered towards that.
We're catered towards stability. And
it's interesting when people talk about,
and I've heard you shoot this down, and
I love how you shoot down this idea that
people should shoot prop daily because
it will give you more of this
fluctuation dayto day. And that's nice
if you read mechanistic theory and
you've never actually practiced in the
field. But when you actually do this and
you work with patients all day every
day, we know that stability is the
number one thing for getting the optimal
outcomes from a hormone replacement
therapy.
>> Right? So the there's a fool out there
who pretends to be a doctor and he's
not. He says that you want to get
spikes. You want to have the highest
amplitude of change. And that might be
true for causing androgen receptor
signaling, but that doesn't mean
androgen receptor signaling inside the
cell causing nuclear transcription
translation. It doesn't mean you're
going to grow more muscle. It means
you're going to get more DHT like side
effects. Because what happens is what
he's not accounting for because he's not
very smart and he's not educated is that
when you have these spikes, your body
will create more five alpha reductes to
deal with those spikes. You get more DHT
response. And so the more DHT response
means you're going to have more
aggression or in theory penis
sensitivity, but if your dick's already
sensitive, it doesn't need to be more
sensitive. That's how you get Minutemen.
And it's like stuff like that. It's
like, and he told me privately three
years ago that the reason why he likes
to use big doses twice a week is because
he likes the way it makes him feel. So,
he's chasing a drug addict high and then
he's trying to retroactively put some
type of pseudocience [__] to justify
his drug-seeking behavior.
And so that's where this whole theory
started with.
>> Yeah. I'm sorry. One of
>> the things I love that you you bring up
is and for for people who are, you know,
listening to the conversation about
steroids, one thing that Todd talks a
lot about his channel is the idea that
unless you are a professional
bodybuilder, you shouldn't be using
anabolic steroids. And one of the things
that I see a lot, you know, in coaching
men and working with clinics where guys
are coming and wanting and everything
from provir to prenabolan and everything
else you hear about online is that
ultimately they're they're basically
looking for drug seeeking behavior.
They're looking for anabolics that will
give them this kind of pseudo
dopamineergic response that they're not
really going to get, but that's what
they're seeking. And it's something that
I really like to shoot down from the
get-go because if we're looking at
testosterone replacement therapy, we're
basically correcting the foundational
biology so that people can go out and
live better lives and feel healthier and
ultimately be better men in the world.
We're not trying to get a recreational
aphrodisiac porn star superman feeling
for a few hours on the testosterone
speaking. And I think a lot of people
are chasing that and they need a reality
check that that's not what we're trying
to achieve with this field of medicine.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, a bodybuilder's
lifestyle is a monk's lifestyle. You
have a regimented eating. You're just
insanely disciplined. So, you're an
insanely disciplined Spartan. You're not
a warrior. You don't hurt anybody, but
you have the same level of discipline of
a Spartan. And you have a very Spartan
existence, if you use the adjective
Spartan, to mean that aesthetic, almost
like a monk-like existence. And so only
someone with that type of inner peace
can be responsible to use, not abuse,
performance-enhancing drugs. It's kind
of like
in martial arts, probably like a
thousand years ago in China, before they
taught you how to break a bone, you had
to learn how to mend a broken bone. So
you had to be able to undo any damage
you do. We have this MMA culture where
everyone learns how to [__] people up,
but no one learns any spirituality to
contain the rage and the damage you can
do. So that's why all these MMA guys go
to jail for beating their wives and
stuff like that is cuz they're you're
teaching the wrong [__] to the wrong
people. So we see that now with the HRT
community where it's almost like an
infection in HRT where these idiots
think that they're entitled to use
anabolic steroids when they don't have
the discipline or the intelligence or
the education to properly use medicine
and their doctors are just as dumb that
they're just criminals in the United
States giving out Anavar or Anadrol or
Deca just because it's the only legal
options not because they're the cleanest
options.
And so you've got this whole wave of
guys over 40 that think that these drugs
are right or you should be on them
because they've been marketed by piece
of [__] [__] who work for TRT
clinics. None of the anabolic steroids
are going to be better than testosterone
for your health. So if your goal is to
be healthy, which all of them say the
same [__] I want to be healthy. I want
to look like a bodybuilder. I just don't
want to do what bodybuilders do. It's
like, okay, so you want to be a
millionaire, but you don't want to get a
[__] job. It's [__] You can't
look like a bodybuilder if you don't do
what bodybuilders do. It's not the
steroids that make us
ideal physically. It's the discipline
that goes into the training and the
nutrition that makes us the ideal human.
And then we look the part because we
walk the walk. That you have to have a
hard mind and a hard heart to have a
hard body. So you've got all these
softhearted, softrained fools who come
in with soft bodies and they think they
can just inject drugs and get hard. It's
not how it works. And so it's not that I
and people like you shouldn't forbid
people from using steroids. It's like
I'm not forbidding anybody. I'm just
saying that it's pointless until you've
mastered testosterone and growth
hormone. You're still HRT once. And if
your goal is to look like a human, you
don't need more than testosterone and
GH. Using anabolic steroids is for
people who've already mastered being a
perfect human and now they want to be
superhuman. They want to be in beyond
human. And so if you're not perfect, you
can't benefit from using steroids yet.
People will say, "Well, you could grow
faster." is like those studies were done
on children like 20-year-old kids who'd
never lifted before and they just gave
them steroids and they said that they
increased in muscle. They didn't
increase in muscle, they increased in
lean body mass. That the eldoststerone
hike that happened from the testosterone
caused them to store more water. So lean
body mass is just fat- free mass. It's
not actual muscle tissue. Water counts
as lean body mass. It's stupid, but it's
true. So, you give a bunch of
20-year-old kids and testosterone and
they gain more lean body mass than the
group of kids who are natural in
lifting. That doesn't mean that they
gain more contractile protein. It means
that they just hold more water. And the
scientists are too [__] stupid to
actually tell the difference between
lean body mass and contractile protein.
They didn't measure the strength gains.
They didn't measure that. They didn't
have guys get shot up on testosterone
for a year and measure them after a year
and no lifting to see what's their um
leg extension on day one, what's their
leg extension on day 366 versus the
group of kids that were natural training
on day one versus day 366
to see, oh, even though they didn't gain
as much weight, the kids who were
lifting and didn't use steroids gained
more strength. Basically, they gained
more muscle mass than the group of kids
that were using just steroids because
they would have had a 10 pound increase
in 12 weeks and they would have stopped
gaining water weight. But these studies
are [__] They're always conducted in
12week period. No one builds any [__]
muscle in 12 weeks. All these studies,
all these outcome studies specifically
are garbage that the only studies that
are really valuable on anabolic
pharmarmacology are mechanistic data.
And then you have to temper that with
experience of actually treating patients
and coaching athletes for stage. When
you have the skill sets of a doctor and
the skill set of a coach and you have
the chemistry background to be able to
read mechanistic data and predict
outcomes, that's when you're able to run
huge experiments that are unofficial
because you're like, "Okay, all these
people are coming to me on primo from
their shitty coaches and they all have
low estrogen. Okay, I'm going to switch
their primo milligram for milligram for
master and their estrogen comes up. They
gain more muscle. They feel better. They
don't gain fat. They don't get gyno. So
that means by definition after a 100,
200, 300 patients, master's better than
primo. It's not like they're leaving me
and going back to their [__] coaches
that were giving them primo. And the
same thing goes for the coaching aspect
is if people are competing and they're
like, "Wow, I've never had a prep this
easy. I've never used this little drugs
and I'm just as dry and just as hard and
I came in fuller using less drugs." It's
like, right, cuz your coach is a [__]
[__] and he just threw drugs at you in
a certain order like, "Oh, it's six
weeks out. We got to add in trend." Or,
"Oh, we've been doing Clen for two
weeks. Let's drop Clen for two weeks."
and then in two weeks put in clen. It's
all this rigor barroll nonsense. It's
based off of [__] people came up
with 30 years ago. And it's none of it's
based off of either outcome studies or
mechanistic data. It's just uneducated
bodybuilders that taught other
uneducated bodybuilders. And it's just
been handed down like an old wives tale
for 30 years. And then the HRT community
is trained by TRT doctors that are
hiring these uneducated bodybuilders to
be salesmen. So they're like, "Okay, you
need we need to put some muscle on so
you're going to have some MK677 so you
can get hungry. Oh, you're too hungry.
Let's give you some ompic so that you
can control your hunger." It's like you
[__] Just take away the MK677.
Don't add ompic to it. And that's how
criminal these TRT clinics are. They're
just throwing drugs at people. I'm
sorry.
>> I'm glad we're going to take a moment
I'm glad we're going to take a moment to
[__] on TRT clinics because uh just like
just like how you have this, you know,
fascinating uh combination of
biochemistry with being an MD as well as
being a professional bodybuilder. My
degrees are in digital marketing and
biomedical science, which I think
qualifies me to [__] on these clinics
because
being having a clinic in Australia and
then over here in Eastern Europe as
well, there's maybe one page of Google
results for the entire Australia TRT
clinics. When I went to visit my friend
Ally Gilbert in Florida, there was like
10 clinics within five kilometers of her
house and it it blew my mind in terms of
how these clinics are operating when
they they look at a a very minimalistic
blood test and then they basically sell
you the the fries and the Coke with your
burger in terms of here's your
testosterone and then here's all the
[__] you don't need. And what they often
do on these sales calls is they hijack
the fear response and they go, "Oh,
well, if you don't take this, this is
going to happen and if you don't take
AI, you're going to get gyno." And
people get bamboozled and they go, "Oh."
and then they make the pick cell. And
what I what I often teach people is that
it's much more cost- effective for these
clinics to have a 100 guys on three
things than 300 guys on one thing
because you've got the economy of scale
of efficiency. So ultimately, when you
go and see a lot of these clinics who
only care about making money and don't
actually care about people, they try to
sell you as many things as possible.
Whereas when you go to someone who knows
what they're doing, when you're asking
for all these things you don't need,
they're going, "No, no, no, no. You
don't need don't need these.
Hey,
hey,
hey.